Guide to the William Thomas Leavell Papers, 1831-1932 RL.10149
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
William Thomas Leavell papers
1831-1932
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Leavell, William Thomas
McDonald, Edward Allen Hitchcock
RL.10149
5.6 Linear Feet 17 boxes; 5,136 items
Collection contains the papers of W. T. Leavell and of his son-in-law, Edward Allen Hitchcock McDonald, Confederate officer, attorney, and businessman. Leavell's papers contain correspondence with leaders of the Episcopal Church concerning church business, doctrinal disputes within the church, and debates between the Episcopal Church and other Protestant denominations; along with family letters and papers which provide information on the salaries, duties, and home life of a minister. The papers of Edward Allen Hitchcock McDonald contain letters from Civil War veterans of McDonald's regiments, the 11th Virginia Cavalry and the 77th Virginia Militia, concerning battles and skirmishes in which they participated; a manuscript copy of McDonald's "The History of the Laurel Brigade," and letters, 1870-1890, pertaining to the Louisville Abstract and Loan Company and general business conditions in Louisville, Ky.
Historical note
William Thomas Leavell was an Episcopal clergyman and farmer, of Charles Town (Jefferson Co.), W. Va.
Collection Overview
Collection comprises the papers of W. T. Leavell and of his son-in-law, Edward Allen Hitchcock McDonald, Confederate officer, attorney, and businessman. Leavell's papers contain correspondence with leaders of the Episcopal Church concerning church business, doctrinal disputes within the church, and debates between the Episcopal Church and other Protestant denominations; and family letters and papers which provide information on the salaries, duties, and home life of a minister.
The papers also contain material pertaining to the economic and agricultural conditions in Leavell's parishes in Virginia and West Virginia and genealogical material on many of his parishioners; letters while a student at Bristol College, Bristol, Pa., 1833-1836, and at Protestant Episcopal Theological Seminary, 1836-37; letters from brothers and sisters in Spotsylvania and Culpeper counties, Va., discussing agriculture; correspondence between daughter Anne Leavell and John M. Daniel in the 1870s, both before and after their respective marriages; and over 200 sermons. Leavell was a teacher at Fairfax Institute, 1837-39. Box 9 contains a diary in which Leavell included much autobiographical information.
The papers of Edward Allen Hitchcock McDonald contain letters from Civil War veterans of McDonald's regiments, the 11th Virginia Cavalry and the 77th Virginia Militia, concerning battles and skirmishes in which they participated; a manuscript copy of McDonald's "The History of the Laurel Brigade," and letters, 1870-1890, pertaining to the Louisville Abstract and Loan Company and general business conditions in Louisville, Ky.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The William Thomas Leavell papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in October, 1947; June 1948; and October 1985.
Agriculture -- Virginia; Virginia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Virginia -- Social conditions; Charles Town (W. Va.); United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Regimental histories; Louisville (Ky.) -- Economic conditions; West Virginia -- Social conditions; Clergy -- Family relationships -- West Virginia; Episcopalian theological seminaries; Confederate States of America. Army. Virginia Cavalry Regiment, 11th; Leavell, William Thomas; McDonald, Edward Allen Hitchcock; McDonald, Ann Leavell; Bristol College (Bucks County, Pa.) -- Students; Louisville Abstract and Loan Company (Louisville, Ky.); Episcopal Church -- Clergy; Episcopal Church -- West Virginia; Protestant Episcopal Theological Seminary in Virginia (Alexandria, Va.) -- Students; Episcopal Church -- Sermons; Virginia. Militia; Episcopal Church -- Virginia; Episcopal Church -- Bishops
- William Thomas Leavell papers, 1832-1932
  - Papers, 1831-1837; 1 boxes (Box 1)
  - Papers, 1838-1841; 1 boxes (Box 2)
  - Papers, 1842-1847; 1 boxes (Box 3)
  - Papers, 1848-1852; 1 boxes (Box 4)
  - Papers, 1853-1857; 1 boxes (Box 5)
  - Papers, 1858-1869; 1 boxes (Box 6)
  - Papers, 1870-1876; 1 boxes (Box 7)
  - Papers, 1877-1889; 1 boxes (Box 8)
  - Papers, 1890-1896; 1 boxes (Box 9)
  - Papers, 1897-1901; 1 boxes (Box 10)
  - Papers, 1902-1932, and undated; 1 boxes (Box 11)
  - Papers, undated; 1 boxes (Box 12)
  - Exercises, miscellaneous, undated; 1 boxes (Box 13)
  - EAH McDonald manuscript: History of the Laurel Brigade, no date; 1 boxes (Box 14)
  - Sermons I, 1 boxes (Box 15)
  - Sermons II, 1 boxes (Box 16)
  - Sermons III, 1 boxes (Box 17)